A Guide to the Registers of Justices of the Virginia Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1818-1858
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Registers of Justices of the Virginia Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1818-1858
The Library of Virginia
36148
7.1 cu. ft. (14 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Commonwealth
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred prior to 1905.
Biographical Information
The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth has evolved from early colonial times when there existed a Secretary of the Colony. Thomas Nelson held the position of the first Secretary of Virginia in 1776. Early Secretaries were elected by the public. An Act of the General Assembly in 1920 changed the election to a joint vote of the General Assembly. In a 1930 Act the duties of the Secretary were redefined with the Secretary of the Commonwealth serving as the ex officio secretary of the Governor, as custodian of many official State records, and as keeper of the Greater and Lesser Seals of the Commonwealth. The office of the Secretary has gradually acquired other functions, such as: service of out-of-state civil process; appointment and regulation of notaries public; and registration and oversight of lobbyists. The Office became a gubernatorial appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office. The Secretary is appointed by the Governor for a term of four years. Currently the Secretary of the Commonwealth is responsible for gubernatorial appointments, clemency and restoration of civil rights requests and extraditions. Additional activities include: serving as ex officio Secretary to the Governor; serving as keeper of the seals of the Commonwealth; compiling and publishing the annual Blue Book; commissioning and regulating notary publics, including the publication of a Notary Handbook and conduct of disciplinary hearings; promulgating the lobbying disclosure requirements, registration of lobbyists, and recording of lobbying reports; servicing the civil process of out-of-state defendants and other parties; and authenticating and certifying the records of the courts and of any state agency.
Scope and Content
Registers of justices, 1818, 1820-1858, listing justices of the peace for counties and cities in Virginia. Many registers also include the names of county and Superior Court clerks, coroners, notary publics, sheriffs, and surveyors. Each list contains name, date commissioned, date qualified, and additional remarks. The additional remarks note if the person had died or resigned and some include personal statements on the justices (ie: they didn't do much business with the court or they never showed up for work). The lists are arranged chronologically, and thereunder alphabetically by county/city with oversize material arranged to the rear.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Albemarle-Cumberland Counties, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Fauquier-Greensville Counties, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Hanover-Lunenburg Counties, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Madison-Nottoway Counties, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Ohio-Williamsburg, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Mason-Wythe Counties, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Naturalization of John Ferguson, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Accomack-Kanawha Counties, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Lee-Wythe Counties, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Accomack-Frederick Counties and Fredericksburg, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Giles-Lunenburg Counties, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Madison-Orange Counties, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Patrick-York Counties, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Accomack-Frederick Counties, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Gloucester-Nottoway Counties, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Ohio-York Counties, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Accomack-Greensville Counties, 1824 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Hampshire-Nottoway Counties, 1824 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Ohio-York Counties, 1824 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Accomack-Essex Counties, 1825 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Fairfax-King William Counties, 1825 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Lancaster-Orange Counties, 1825 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Patrick-York Counties, 1825 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1826 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Mathews-Wythe Counties, 1826 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Accomack-Essex Counties, 1827 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Fairfax-King William Counties, 1827 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Lancaster-Nottoway Counties, 1827 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Ohio-Wood Counties, 1827 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Albemarle-Louisa Counties, 1828 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Mason-York Counties, 1828 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1829 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Mathews-Wythe Counties, 1829 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1830 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Mason-Wythe Counties, 1830 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Accomack-Ohio Counties, 1831 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Patrick-Wythe Counties, 1831 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Accomack-Franklin Counties, 1832 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Gloucester-King and Queen Counties, 1832 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Lancaster-Nottoway Counties, 1832 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Ohio-Wythe Counties, 1832 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Accomack-King William Counties, 1833 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Lancaster-Wythe Counties, 1833 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Alleghany-Morgan Counties, 1834 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Nansemond-York Counties, 1834 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Accomack-Louisa Counties, 1835 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Marshall-Wythe Counties, 1835 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Accomack-King William Counties, 1836 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Lancaster-Wood Counties, 1836 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Amelia-King William Counties, 1837 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Lancaster-Westmoreland Counties and Williamsburg, 1837 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1838 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Marshall-Wood Counties, 1838 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1839 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Marshall-York Counties, 1839 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Accomack-King William Counties, 1840 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Loudoun-York Counties, 1840 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1841 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Madison-Wythe Counties, 1841 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1842 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Marion-Wood Counties, 1842 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Accomack-King William Counties, 1843 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Lancaster-Wood Counties, 1843 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Accomack-King George Counties, 1844 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Lancaster-York Counties, 1844 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Accomack-Cumberland Counties, 1845 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Dinwiddie-Henry Counties, 1845 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Isle of Wight-Nottoway Counties, 1845 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Ohio-York Counties, 1845 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1846 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Madison-York Counties, 1846 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1847 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Marion-York Counties, 1847 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1848 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Marion-York Counties, 1848 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Accomack-Buckingham Counties, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Cabell-Frederick Counties and Fredericksburg, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Giles-Isle of Wight Counties, 1849 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Jackson-Lunenburg Counties, 1849 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Madison-Nottoway Counties, 1849 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Ohio-Putnam Counties, 1849 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Randolph-Sussex Counties, 1849 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Taylor-York Counties, 1849 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Accomack-Morgan Counties, 1850 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Nansemond-York Counties, 1850 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Accomack-Lunenburg Counties, 1851 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Marshall-York Counties, 1851 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Accomack-Essex Counties, 1852 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Fairfax-Morgan Counties, 1852 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Nansemond-Wyoming Counties, 1852 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Accomack-Greensville Counties, 1853-1858 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Hampshire-Louisa Counties, 1853-1858 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Mecklenburg-Ohio Counties, 1853-1858 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Page-Wyoming Counties, 1853-1858 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Brooke-Spotsylvania Counties [oversize], 1818 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Spotsylvania-Tyler Counties [oversize], 1822 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Fluvanna County [oversize], 1823 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Pittsylvania-York Counties [oversize], 1827 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Fairfax-Tazewell Counties [oversize], 1828 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Dinwiddie-York Counties [oversize], 1829 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Brunswick-York Counties [oversize], 1830 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Albemarle-York Counties [oversize], 1831 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Augusta-York Counties [oversize], 1832 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Cabell-Powhatan Counties [oversize], 1833 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Dinwiddie-Powhatan Counties [oversize], 1834 (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Caroline-Powhatan Counties [oversize], 1835 (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Augusta-Richmond Counties [oversize], 1836 (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Braxton-Richmond Counties [oversize], 1837 (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Cumberland-Powhatan Counties [oversize], 1838 (Box 14, Folder 15)
- Bedford-Spotsylvania Counties [oversize], 1839 (Box 14, Folder 16)
- Augusta-Randolph Counties [oversize], 1840 (Box 14, Folder 17)
- Clarke-Powhatan Counties [oversize], 1841 (Box 14, Folder 18)
- Augusta-Spotsylvania Counties [oversize], 1842 (Box 14, Folder 19)
- Buckingham-Richmond Counties [oversize], 1843 (Box 14, Folder 20)
- Clarke-Powhatan Counties [oversize], 1844 (Box 14, Folder 21)
- Clarke-Warren Counties [oversize], 1845 (Box 14, Folder 22)
- Clarke-Richmond Counties [oversize], 1846 (Box 14, Folder 23)
- Clarke-Powhatan Counties [oversize], 1847 (Box 14, Folder 24)
- Clarke-Powhatan Counties [oversize], 1848 (Box 14, Folder 25)
- Clarke-Tyler Counties [oversize], 1849 (Box 14, Folder 26)
- Clarke-Tyler Counties [oversize], 1850 (Box 14, Folder 27)
- Clarke-Powhatan Counties [oversize], 1851 (Box 14, Folder 28)
- Hampshire and Powhatan Counties [oversize], 1854-1857 (Box 14, Folder 29)